[Music]
and we are live
good evening good day everybody hope
you're doing well
and welcome to the third episode of ask
abhijeet
today is the chingish khan special the
mongolia special
so before we begin a couple of things
today i have enabled the slow chat
so the chat will happen a little slower
than yesterday
and i also have a moderator who's
moderating the discussion
so what happened yesterday was that
there were so many chat messages that i
missed many of the good questions i
missed many of the super chats that were
purchased
so to those of you whose questions i
missed and whose super chats i missed i
apologize
uh i'm still learning so today will be a
better experience
and those of you who have purchased
super chats that i've missed i'm gonna
do a special episode tomorrow
7 p.m india time 7 in the evening and
i'm going to cover all the
missed super chats that i have missed in
the first two episodes thus far
so that's what i'll do tomorrow and so
today let's come to today's
topic which is khan and you all may be
wondering why
am i talking about this chingish khan or
changes khan or genghis khan this person
what is his relevance why should we why
should we bother about him
so so here's the thing let me show you
his empire he
see chinese khan is one of the greatest
he's not one of the greatest he is the
greatest
conqueror of all time and let me show
you what his
empire looked like so this is
the empire of chinggis khan and his
descendants this is in 1279.
he died in 1227. so this so the western
region the european region was conquered
by his descendants by his sons and
grandsons
but everything else was conquered by
himself
now as you can see there is one very
interesting and very big
piece of the map missing in his empire
and that is obviously india so for some
reason this guy who conquered half the
world
did not conquer india and that's what
has always fascinated and intrigued me
for a very long time
so i started reading about chingis khan
in the year 2000
that's 21 years ago and i have read a
lot about him and i have found that he
has been
misportrayed very badly he has been
demonized by
almost every historian until very
recently
and so by doing a lot of reading and all
i was able to uncover what he truly was
like
and there was one question that nobody
has answered in the past 700 years
which is why did why did chhingiskan
refuse to conquer india
so i was able to essentially figure out
what what was the reason for that
and i have made a video about that which
went absolutely viral it has
more than 1.8 million views in the past
five months so maybe you can check it
out to get some background
later so that is what we're going to
discuss so let me just give you a brief
brief introduction about this
so in the year 1221
exactly 800 years before today
jungis khan was in punjab he was at the
western
border of india he was in the indus
valley and he was pursuing a guy called
jalaluddin who was the last
shah of the khwarasm empire which is
iran and central asia so he was pursuing
jalaluddin jalaluddin tried to come into
india to get refuge with the mamluk
dynasty
the indian uh mamluk king was
a turk so chingas khan came all the way
pursuing
jalaluddin into india and he was able to
destroy
jalaluddin's army entirely in the battle
of the indus in the year 1221
and then he turned back even though he
was at the border of india the richest
country in the history of the world
the country with the highest gdp of all
time
he could have conquered it the mom looks
the islamic
invaders of india were no match for
ching his khan absolutely no match for
him
but he decided to turn back and that is
a great mystery that has been a great
mystery for 800 years
until i was the first person to give an
answer as to
why he chose to turn back so i have
realized that i seem to be the only
expert on chinggis khan in india
so i thought let me do this session so
there are a lot of misconceptions about
this person
this guy chingish khan conquered more
land in 30 years than all the roman
emperors could conquer
in 300 years that is how great a
conqueror he was
and yet he invaded other kingdoms and
empires only in retaliation
he did not ever start a war but he
always finished the wars
so that's the guy that's the kind of guy
he was and
as to why he refused to invade india he
had there was a number of reasons
but one of the reasons was that he had a
strong
affinity for indian culture he was a he
was not a buddhist
but he was a big fan of buddhism and
buddhism
is another form of hinduism which is
what i have already
said in the past so that's why he he had
a great deal of respect for buddhism and
hinduism
and he did not want to spill the blood
spill any blood in the land that gave
birth to buddhism and hinduism
and that is one of the reasons one of
the several reasons why he chose not to
invade india so that
is a brief amount of background
and context about shingis khan
so and there are a lot of misconceptions
in india about this man most of
us in india believe that he was a muslim
right and we most of us believe that the
mongols were muslims and that
khan is an islamic surname and many
people seem to believe that
alauddin khilji defeated chengiskan six
times or seven times
and people seem to believe that the
islamic invader
timur was a descendant of chiggas khan
and that babar and the mughals were
descendants of chinese khan
there is this uh this belief that chung
is khan fathered thousands of children
and 10 to 20 of humanity is descended
from him
and much more so let's deal with all of
these questions
one by one so let me take uh
start by taking a couple of questions so
here we are thank you very much
grip get it uh the question is your
shingiskan video is my favorite history
video ever on youtube thank you so much
question in your opinion expertise what
was the factor or factors that made
khan and the mongols the most effective
conquerors
ever that is a great question it goes to
the heart of the matter
as to how these one man and and his
descendants were able to conquer the
greatest empire
in history he was greater than julius
caesar greater than alexander there's a
so-called great
and every other conqueror so great
question let's
go into that so the first thing is that
the mongols were nomads they live in
mongolia which is
essentially a wasteland of very barren
and harsh land it's it's frozen for
great
for great periods of the of the year the
mongol and winter is extremely harsh
temperatures routinely go to minus 30
degrees and
even in springtime and summer food is
very scarce and it's
it's a very tough life in mongolia so
the mongols have been nomads
for about 2000 years they're still
nomads many of them are still
living a nomadic lifestyle which is what
they prefer
so they have always been a mobile nation
a nomadic nation and living in such a
harsh environment
requires a lot of discipline almost
military discipline
so the mongols were in the past divided
into various ethnic
not ethnic groups but uh clans and
tribes
and they were always at war with each
other and they were always for centuries
invaded by the chinese repeatedly so
they always had to
be on the alert and they were always
trying to survive
so they were accustomed to a great deal
of hardship
they were accustomed to moving all the
time and they were accustomed to
military
discipline and that is the world that
jingis khan was born into
so what this man achieved ching is khan
in the first 45 or so years of his life
was he unified the entire mongolian
nation
unified all the clans and tribes and he
created unified nation
so that is the first achievement and he
did it because of his military prowess
and his tactical and strategic
superiority and then he invaded china
and he what he did
while invading china was he acquired as
much
chinese military technology as he could
so that mongols where they did not care
whether the cat was black or white as
long as it caught mice
so they acquired as much technology as
they could it did not matter where the
technology came from
they took it and they used it so in a
very
short amount of time they acquired a
great deal of expertise they acquired
all possible different kinds of
technology
armor crossbows catapults siege engines
and much more they learn new tactics and
strategies from the chinese generals
and engineers that they that they
captured and
what they did was that they incorporated
these uh
conquered peoples into their army
and they treated them very nicely so so
they acquired a great deal of expertise
by doing that
and the other thing is that their
tactics and strategies were brilliant
uh we have heard of the so-called
blitzkrieg strategy that the nazi
nazis used in the second world war well
the blitzkrieg's
quick strategy is essentially
concentrating all your firepower
all your weaponry into one spot and
blasting a hole through the enemy
defenses
and then just pushing through and
conquering the territory so that
is called blitzkrieg it means lightning
warfare in german
well the blitzkrieg strategy is actually
a mongolian strategy the mongols
pioneered it
and they used it to devastating effect
everywhere they went
so that is one of the things the other
thing was that the mongols had
uh they were very mobile they could
cover
incredible distances in very short times
because of the
because of the pony the mongolian pony
which is a which is a specific
uh special breed of horse that is native
to mongolia
even the indian manipuri horse is
closely related to the mongolian pony
so this is a short horse but it's very
tough it has
immense stamina and it is capable of
immense bursts of speed
so that is one of this one of the
weapons one of the
strengths that the mongols had and they
had a dizzying array of tactics and
strategies
all of which was basically
meant for one objective only to defeat
and destroy the enemy
and the other thing was that their
communications were brilliant they could
communicate
and coordinate two different armies
even 200 kilometers apart in almost real
time
so they could envelop the enemy from
different angles
outflank them and coordinate attacks
from
very different geographical areas
apparently at the same time
so these are some of the reasons why
chinggis khan and the mongols were
so incredibly successful the world had
never seen anything like them
and they conquered so much territory in
such a short period of time
so i hope that throws some kind of
light on on this matter so great
question and thank you for that
let me take one more question
okay this is from dev chaturmati
chaturvedi
thank you dave who is the greatest
emperor of all time tell us
ching is khan absolutely no question
about it changes khan is the greatest
emperor of all time
not just because he was a great
conqueror
not just because he conquered so much
territory but because he was a wise
and just ruler he is portrayed as a
barbarian everywhere you see
the western historians even the islamic
historians have portrayed him as a
bloodthirsty savage
a monster a barbarian you know that's
how he has been portrayed
but a man like him
if he was a bloodthirsty barbarian
just being a bloodthirsty barbarian and
a savage and a brutal
oppressive ruler is not enough to make
you
conquer so much territory you need an
immense amount of intelligence
and coordination and planning and
logistical ability
and so much more to be able to do this
and he had all of that
and the thing about him is that the
territory that he conquered
he ruled it and administered it very
justly
he had the same set of rules for all his
subjects
mongolians and conquered peoples alike
so he had
he had a code of laws called the yasa
low
the yasa code of laws it was applicable
it was applied
very strictly it was enforced very
strictly and very harshly
everybody was subject to it even his own
family members
all right and it was a very strict call
of laws and
it was fair it was hard but it was fair
so if you transgressed the laws you had
to deal with the punishment no matter
who you were
even if you were a member of the of the
golden family chinese khan's own family
so these are some of the reasons why he
was so great he was one of the greatest
emperors
he was definitely the greatest emperor
of all time and he had a set of
principles he had a set of morals
you know some people lack principles
their only principle
their only morality is is plunder and
conquest
i want to i want to rob as much i want
to rob as many people as possible
and enrich myself ching is khan was not
motivated by
wealth and i can prove it to you he
conquered
an enormous amount of territory
here we go this is most of it and yet he
did not engage
in colonialism there is an immense
difference between conquest
and colonialism ching is khan conquered
he did not loot
he did not steal he did not impoverish
the lands he conquered
look at mongolia today is there any vast
amount of wealth
mongolia is essentially a poor country
even today which
tells you that this man did not extract
wealth out of the terror
out of the conquered territories compare
that with the european colonizers
they destroyed impoverished and pillaged
every
land they conquered look at what they
did to india india went from being the
greatest
the most prosperous economy in the world
more than one third of the entire world
gdp to less than two two percent of the
world gdp
in just two and a half centuries under
the british
so they finished extracting the entirety
of india's wealth in two and a half
centuries
that's what the british did they
destroyed the country in all ways
the mongols never did that so that
these are some of the reasons why
chinese khan was so great
he was not just a great conqueror but he
was a fair and just
ruler so i hope that answers your
question thank you for the question
all right let me go to the next question
what is the history behind the name of
the mughal empire this is by abhijit
deshpande thank you abhijeet
good question so the the name the mughal
empire makes it sound like these are
mongols right
now when these so-called mughals invaded
india they called themselves
they spoke turkic languages most of them
spoke the chagatai language i believe
uh the so-called slave dynasty mamluk
dynasty
[Music]
etc their mother tongue was chagatai
so that is a turkic language it seems to
be connected to the mongols because
genghis khan's son's name was chagatai
but chagatai the language was a turkic
language
all right so these islamic invaders of
india
including the so-called mughals were
actually turks
and the indians called these people
turks and they
themselves called themselves turks but
it is the british
in their revised history of india in the
macaulayan education system
it is the british who started calling
them mughals and that's why we still
go on using that same terminology they
were not mughals
they were not mongols they did not
practice mongolian culture they did not
practice tangirism buddhism hinduism any
of that
right the so-called mughals practiced
islam they did not speak a mongolian
language they spoke
turkic languages so they were turks in
all ways
so that is the very brief history about
the mughal empire
that it originated as turkic invaders
they were not mongols
now who are these turkic invaders did
they have mongolian ancestry some of
them did
what happened was that chinese khan
conquered such an enormous empire
that after his deaths after his death
it was divided into very large pieces
and all of
each of these peace pieces was
administered and ruled by one of his
sons
now though those of his sons and
descendants who ruled the
islamic parts of the world eventually
became turkish
they married among the turkish people
this they adopted turkish
customs and the language and the islamic
religion
and eventually they became turks so
their mongolian identity was erased very
quickly
in just a couple of generations or three
fourth generations down the line
so they may have had some mongolian
blood but they were
turkic in all ways so that is a very big
misconception among indians that the
mughals were mongols they were not
mongols they were turks
thank you for your question okay next
okay this is a question by ankur saksena
you think the invasion
of chinggis khan would have been better
for india
he was a great ruler and a man with
principles
well here's the thing
shingis khan was clearly a very
uh principled ruler he administered
the territories that he conquered very
fairly and justly
so had he conquered india and whenever
he conquered he did not destroy the
native culture
he did not try to impose his language
and his religion
and his lifestyle and his traditions on
the conquered people
so that is one thing that is to be noted
so
had he conquered india he would have not
tried to destroy india's culture
and destroy india's cultural artifacts
and impose a mongolian culture in india
he would definitely not have done that
one bit the other thing to be noted
is that when shingis khan conquered the
kharasma empire which is iran
turkmenistan
kazakhstan etc central asia when he
conquered
this islamic heartland one of the
strange things he did was that he
replaced
mosques with buddhist temples so
there's a back story to this central
asia was
indianized for thousands of years it it
was home to
indianized dynasties and indianized
people who were the descendants of
indian migrants to the west which these
migrations happened thousands of years
ago
and most of these dynasties claimed
descent from
the vedic clans of india so indeed
so the central asian region was for a
very very long time
home to indianized cultures and peoples
right and you will
you will find signs of this everywhere
you will see ruined temples
and rural monasteries and ruined
buddhist structures
everywhere in afghanistan in kazakhstan
in turkmenistan
even in the caucasus region everywhere
and
many and after this this region became
islamized
many of these buddhist monasteries which
may have been hindu temples in the past
many of these dharmic structures were
destroyed
and replaced with mosques and when you
replace
an ancient structure with a mosque you
usually what they would usually do is
they would
repurpose the architecture they would
repurpose the bricks
and stones into making the mosque so
when chingas can't reach here
i'm sure he could see that the this
these mosques were originally
buddhist monuments so what he did was in
many places he
brought these mosques down and put
buddhist temples in their place all over
again
and after his descendants became
islamized the mosques
came up again all over again so the
point i'm making is that he was a
he was a big fan of buddhism
and by extension of hinduism
so had he conquered india he would not
he would
100 not have destroyed any buddhist
temples or hindu temples
he would actually have promoted the
religion and culture that is what i
believe i mean that is
very apparent from the pattern of
behavior that he has already exhibited
and that he is he is known to have
exhibited
so would his invasion have been better
than better for india than the turkic
invasions
or 100 absolutely india would have been
a very
different country today but that is all
hypothetical history because we know
what
actually what actually happened
right so thank you for your question let
me look at other questions
okay
okay this is this is a question by
chetan what is your opinion on the thank
you chetan
for the super chat what's your opinion
on the idea of nations considering it's
relatively a very fresh concept
will we see civilizations back in the
future the chinese
are it's a good question very good
question the concept of nation states is
very new
it's very recent it's about uh two it's
about 300 or so
years old plus or minus something or the
other
historically as long as humankind has
existed we have not had
nation states we've only had
kings and kingdoms and empires at time
and civilizations so the chinese
are trying to portray themselves as a
civilization not as a nation-state
and that's why the their expansionist
behavior
is in in a way explained off by that
that we are a civilization
we will expand because civilizations
have all
are always a net exporter of culture and
other things and they have
a military sphere of influence that
transcends that geographical boundaries
so the chinese are already trying to
portray themselves as a civilization
state
india has defined itself as a nation
state in 1947
by which it officially ceased to be a
civilization which is a really stupid
thing to do in my opinion
so i believe that going forward in the
future we will see the resurgence of
civilizations
the nation-state idea is a brief
experiment it is a few centuries long
which is an eye blink of time in the
broader context of human history
so it's a it's a western concept it
stems from the st from the treaty of
westphalia in europe a few centuries ago
in which europe was divided up into
small kingdoms and fiefdoms
into small nation states for the local
rulers to exploit
so it's a very exploitative idea it is
not really
empowering for the people despite
external appearances
the natural state of being for human
uh cultures and societies has been has
been either
kingdoms or civilizations or empires
and it's it's not about the merits and
demerits of the thing
which is morally superior which is
morally inferior as a realist as a
student of history i would say that this
is a temporary
experiment it may not last long in the
future we may revert to civilizations
so china is one which is behaving like a
civilization state
russia is also behaving like a
china and russia are very clear about
the fact that they reject
the concept of democracy they don't
believe in it and they're gonna do it
do the things their own way so in the
future others may also follow suit
and revert to their traditional
indigenous form of governance and
administration
so excellent question
next question by mohit
why were the mughals able to conquer
most of india but not able to
enter the southern part that is lower
under pradesh and
tamil nadu uh that's an excellent
question
and i don't think anyone has answered
this question thus far
i would say that the moguls were
actually not that powerful
the reason the the mughals were able to
conquer and subdue
large parts of india the reason for that
was that it
they they invaded india at a time when
india was fragmented politically
so india has seen cycles of history
there have been cycles where india has
been united
under a single emperor as in the mauryan
emperors or the gupta emperors or the
kushan emperors like kanishka so there
were times when india was
united under a single emperor and there
were times where india was fragmented
into numerous kingdoms
sometimes it was the mahajanapadas
sometimes it was the rajput
feudal states etc but it's always been
one culture and one civilization
so these islamic invaders the turks
entered india conquered india
invaded india at a time at a phase of
india's history when india was
disunited and that is the primary reason
why
despite not being that great a military
power the
turkic invaders were able to quickly
conquer large parts of india
not very large parts but at least large
parts of northern and western
india now in the south you had powerful
kingdoms
powerful empires the vijayanagara empire
was incredibly powerful
the tamils also had powerful uh empires
and kings and all that
and these were able to resist the the
turks
for longer periods of time uh the
vijayanagara empire fell
fell very tragically uh because of
treachery and all that
so that is something that india has
always must
always uh uh
be that india needs to always keep an
eye on that there is
always the possibility of treachery so
that is the reason why the vijayanagara
empire fell
but in the south of india it was
basically
to some extent insulated because of the
enormous geography of india it was
insulated from these invasions
and therefore tamil nadu especially was
able to escape the
the turkic invasions and it took them a
great deal of time before they were able
to
conquer vijayanagar and some parts of
some other parts of southern india
so cover so there's a number of reasons
for this but
it's primarily because they were not as
powerful as we think they are
and secondly because india is so large
we see
india as one piece in the map but it's
actually an enormous
subcontinent-sized piece of geography so
the distances were against the the
mughals and the turks and that's why
they were not able to
conquer and subdue parts of southern
india
so i hope that answers your question
let me see
okay this is from rohit badani it's not
related to changi khan but let me
quickly answer this
would you please elaborate on northeast
india and how its history evolved and
what impact it had
made on other kingdoms at that point in
time so the north
east part of india is actually the
eastern part of india we call it the
northeast because of
i don't know why it's called the
northeast but let's just call it the
northeast for now
so it's a fascinating part of india it's
a
very interesting mix of cultures
and ethnicities so you have assam you
have manipur you have
so called nagaland mizoram
tripura sikkim arunachal pradesh
and that entire region so today it is uh
we have very well defined boundaries but
in the past you had kingdoms that
expanded and shrunk
for example the kingdom kingdom of
manipur was much larger at certain
points in time
manipur had conquered parts of burma the
manipuri king even conquered rangoon
at one point and even some parts of the
yunnan region of
of present-day china the homs were
a magnificent dynasty a great dynasty
they also had
a rich diverse culture and they have
made
a great deal of cultural contribution to
to to
the whole of india essentially the
homs are essentially a tibet of burman
people they are
a local manifestation of the thai people
the thai people
are found throughout this region
thailand the country gets its name from
the thai people it's
thailand actually and the people of the
yunnan region of china
are also of thai ethnicity they are not
chinese
yunnan doesn't belong in china and
similarly they are homs as well
so this is an ethnic group that is
present that is spread out over a
very large geographical area and they
have been indianized
for for almost 2000 years the thais the
the yunnan people
and the ahms they were all they all are
indianized
to various degrees and in various forms
so the home empire was brilliant it was
great it repulsed
the mughal incursions on numerous
occasions
they were very brave they had a great
military history
so that is very briefly about the
northeast of india
it has evolved for i would say
several thousand years the oldest
recorded history of the
of this region is i believe it is the
chaitarol kumbaba which is the manipuri
chronicle of kings which goes back at
least
2000 years probably much before that
and unfortunately our historians are not
interested in researching these matters
so i hope that changes in the future
but that is very briefly about the
northeast of india it's a fascinating
brilliant brilliant place
and it deserves much more attention than
it gets
okay next question
thomas schiff was india's outlook
towards sex and pornography more liberal
did
abrahamic invasions influence this
mindset as we consider it today
okay once again it's not related to
change khan but let me quickly answer
this
india i don't know what liberal means is
it
liberal in the modern context
see india has been a very open society
in the past just look at the temples in
khajuraho and you can see
that sex was not taboo if you look at
ancient
indian sculptures of men and women you
will see that they were dressed
according to the india
to india's climate india's climate to
the most part
is rather hot in the southern regions of
india it is quite humid
so you should not i mean it is not
natural
for the people of these climates to wear
extensive
amounts of clothing so you can see that
in ancient indian
scar carvings and sculptures you will
see men and women who are topless
it was not a big deal at all that was
the
that was the way of the way of living so
and about sex and pornography i mean you
can see
sculptures of sexual acts and all kinds
of things
uh so it was by no means taboo at all
so india was a very open society if you
look at indianized
cultures in eastern asia you will see a
much more relaxed outlook towards uh
towards basically sexuality and that is
essentially what india
also had if you look at a country like
thailand for example
they have absolutely no problem with any
sort of sexuality
whether it is the normal straight
sexuality or or homosexuality
or trans people or transgenders or
anything
everything is accepted everything is is
fine no one cares
you do your your thing will do our thing
so that's how india has always been
today india is a much more closed
society with respect to
to displays of sexuality and unity and
all that and
clearly this happened after the
abrahamic invasions so that is the
answer in short
this is a donation by ss thank you so
much no question
thank you very much i appreciate it okay
let me take some more
questions abhishek banerjee thank you
can you make a video about hitler's
third reich and his ss
battalions that's an interesting topic i
will
add it to my possible future videos list
thank you let me take some questions
about
chingus khan and the mongols
okay this is a question by dhruva
anindya ghosh
where the mongols ethnically proto-hands
and where the hans
the proto turks brilliant brilliant
question
you're going to the heart of the matter
over here so
here's the deal the mongols and the
turks
essentially are the same people if you
go back 2000 years two and a half
thousand years
they have the same ancestors their
ancestors were the huns the
peoples so if you see that if you see
the
history of the turks before they became
islamized
they practiced the same culture and
religion as the mongols
they practiced tangirism which is a
polytheistic pantheistic
religion with with elements of nature
worship shaman
shamanism animism ancestor worship
and much more it has an entire pantheon
of gods and goddesses
which is strikingly similar to vedic
hinduism
so this is the belief system
that the mongols practiced and the turks
also practiced this before they became
islamized the turks were buddhists
at some points in time and and that's
the history that they had
so the mongols are the descendants of
the huns not the hans
the huns and the turks are also the
descendants of the huns
and the hoans went all the way into
europe attila
who sacked rome was a hun he's called
attila
and the the magyars the people of
hungary
well they are also the product of an
ancient
hunnic invasion of of europe
so there's a very interesting history
the homes are very fascinating people
and they spawned these two separate
ethnicities
the turks and the mongols but the turks
and the mongols have a great deal of
similarity
for example when when mustafa kemal
atathur
embarked upon his turkishization process
when he his turkification process after
winning the turkish war of independence
in the 1920s
what he the first thing he did was to
sanitize the turkish language
and remove all arabic and persian words
from the turkic language from the
turkish language
and he replaced these persian and arabic
words
with mongolian equivalent words with
mongolian synonyms
so he recognized the fact that mongolian
language and culture is very
close and similar to turkish culture and
that the turks are essentially the
descendants of the proto-hans the
proto-mongols proto-hunts
and proto-mongols and we don't
realize this but there has been
a wave of hunnic invasions into india
they were called the shweta hunas in
sanskrit in english the hephthalites
this happened more than 1500 years ago
the many of these waves of invasion by
the horns were repulsed eventually
the horns did break through they did
conquer parts of india
northern india they did conquer parts of
afghanistan which was very much part of
india at that time
and they assimilated harmoniously into
indian society
some of them practiced hinduism some of
them practiced buddhism
and they defended india and india's
national interest
it's very interesting and they promoted
india's culture for example
the great mathematician astronomer
brahma gupta
his patron was a king
of the chapat of the shri chapa dynasty
whose name was vyagra mukher
and vyagamukha was a first generation or
second generation in
immigrant into india his father or
grandfather was a
hunik invader so this guy the descendant
the son or grandson of invaders was the
patron of one one of india's greatest
scientists and he was also a patron of
the arts and
culture so the first wave of hunic
invasions into india
you could call them the first wave of
first wave of turkic invasions
was a very different wave in many ways
than the second wave which is the
so-called mughals
so the original turkic invaders of india
the original invaders of india
were very much assimilated into indian
society and
and their decisions probably live among
us today
so to go back to your questions the
mongols
are the descendants of the huns and so
are the turks
okay some more questions
okay this is by dungar singh chauhan
thank you
for this question there is a
long-running
fact or story that changes khan slept
with so many women
that in today's world every one in 200
people are related to him
please give your opinion very good
question i'm glad you bring this up so
this is a
very popular belief that at least 10
percent of humanity
minimum is descended from ching is khan
because
he slept with or rather raped
thousands of women and fathered
thousands and fathered thousands of
children
this is a very popular belief today all
across the world
and the origin of this belief is a
national geographic article from i think
2003 or thereabouts
and the title of the article was
something like chingas khan was a
prolific
lover and that he fathered thousands of
children
so the basis of this article is a
suppose is a genetic study
that found that there is a certain
mongolian lineage a patrilineal
genetic lineage which traces back to
mongolia
that is found in large parts of central
asia
and in some parts of europe so they have
made the leap of imagination
of connecting that lineage with changes
khan
now if you want to connect two
individuals
genetically you need dna samples of both
both individuals
right so let's say that we find a person
who has this mongolian genetic lineage
who is alive today you take that blood
or or a piece of hair or something
you do a dna test you sample that genome
and then you would need to connect that
person to chinggis khan genetically
so you would need a sample of
chingishan's dna a strand of hair a
piece of bone or something but
we don't have that we do not have a
single sample of changes dna
because his tomb has never been found
right
so then how do you make the conclusion
that this genetic lineage is is uh
fathered by chingus khan
when you don't have a sample of his dna
and you don't even have a sample of dna
from any of his descendants
any of his sons or grandsons so how does
one make this incredible leap of
of of of belief
so this article is completely erroneous
it is
scientifically wrong and this
essentially is another
example of the way ching is khan has
been demonized relentlessly
throughout history there is absolutely
no evidence that he raped women
or slept with hundreds of women and and
the other
uh popular uh belief is that the mongols
used rape as a weapon of war which means
that they were systematic
they were systematic rapists once again
there is not
one shred of of real hard evidence
that corroborates this fact now the
most of the histories of the mongols
have been written by their enemies
these histories have been written by the
people they conquered and therefore they
have been obviously
demonized in these histories but there
is no real evidence
no hard scientific evidence that
corroborates any of these claims
for example some english historian
actually portrayed the mongols as
cannibals
as they reported them as eating the
flesh of their
of the people they conquer which is
obviously a complete lie
so this is the way the mongols have been
relentlessly demonized
now the fact is this the mongols had a
code of laws called the yasa code
it was instituted by chinese khan and
this code of laws
was very very strictly and harshly
enforced
and this this code of laws prescribed
the death penalty for anyone who
who either abducted or sexually molested
a woman and this applied to any person
inside his enormous empire so every
woman in his empire was protected by
this law
whether she was mongol or from a
conquered people every woman in this
empire
was protected by chinese khan's law now
tell me
this is a man who is the ruler who is
the leader of an enormous nation
now would he have been able to garner
the respect of his soldiers
and his people had he been flouting his
own laws
can a leader claim to be a leader
if he is breaking the laws that he is
imposing on on his own on his subjects
it just doesn't work that way changes
khan was universally respected by his
people
and even by his enemies so this
story this incredibly poor
myth that he was a mass rapist and that
the mongols were rapists
it is a lie it is an absolute lie there
is no
it has no basis in fact
okay next question
by dr heinz doofenshmirtz thank you dr
heinz
did any indian ruler ever ruled tibet
specifically mount kailash
how is japanese shinto and chinese
taoism related to our
culture so did
indian rulers rule tibet so we had
indian ice kingdoms
north of the himalayas they present a
so-called xinjiang region of china
has was was indianized for many many
millennia most likely and the gandhari
language
was the lingua franca throughout central
asia and north of the himalayas
in the so-called xinjiang region today
the city of kashgar was known as
kashinagar
in the past and many of these
city-states
north of the himalayas were founded by
indians for example one of these cities
was founded by indians during the
mauryan times
so there were many rulers in this part
of the world the tibetan
uh people they became a
a separate distinct culture and nation
approximately 2000 years ago
or thereabouts give or take a couple of
centuries
so before that definitely there were
indians who ruled that entire region
and the himalayas were never actually
patrolled and ruled
it was just a mountainous region of
course mount kailash is the most
sacred mountain for for indians and
other people as well
it is the holiest mountain in hinduism
in buddhism
and in the tibetan born religion so
yes this region has been under the
jewish section of indian kings who ruled
north of the himalayas
on on several occasions most of the time
nobody has laid
claim to this region it's always been
ungoverned because nobody could
could live in that environment but it
has always been under the indian sphere
of influence
tibet is essentially
an indianized culture so so that's
that's the thing that's that's the
answer if tibet was still
independent today i imagine that the
relationship between india and tibet
would have been like the current
relationship between india and nepal
open borders and no passport and no
visas
that's the relationship we would have
had with them had we
saved them from the chinese invasion so
that's part one of your question
part two is how is japanese shinto and
chinese taoism related to our culture
so let's take shinto so for many many
centuries
so so buddhism and hinduism entered
japan approximately 1500 years ago
now the japanese consider themselves to
be buddhists those who practice buddhism
but if you look beneath the surface
there are
lots of elements of hinduism in japanese
buddhism
most of the gods and goddesses of hindu
of hinduism
are worshiped in japan under japanese
name
for example one of their goddesses is
the great goddess bin zaitan
who is saraswati it is the japanese name
for saraswati
they worship ganesh as well ganesh has a
japanese name
kuber has a japanese name lord shiva has
a japanese name
so essentially every indian god and
goddess every hindu god and goddess
is worshipped as part of japanese
buddhism so
that again corroborates my claim that
buddhism is just another form
of hinduism so japanese so the
indigenous religion of japan is shinto
it is the belief system of japan it is
once again
a very uh it's a polytheistic belief
system
the local gods are called kami so there
are elements of nature worship and
spirit worship and ancestor worship
and animism in shinto so when buddhism
entered japan like any polytheistic
belief system
it it harmoniously
syncretized itself with the indigenous
japanese religion
so for centuries you had the same temple
for shinto practices as well as buddhist
practices
now in the 19th century there was this
so-called meiji
uh meiji reformation the meiji emperor
tried to reform japan
and he tried to portray buddhism as a
foreign religion he tried to
stamp out buddhism by force and he
failed
but what he succeeded in doing was he he
succeeded in creating a perception that
buddhism is a foreign import into japan
so now you have separate temples for
shinto
practices and for buddhist practices but
overall it's a very syncretic culture
so that is how shinto is shin the
japanese shinto religion
is closely integrated and syncretized
with
indian culture and buddhism and hinduism
and the same goes for chinese taoism
taoism is a chinese
indigenous practice but china is today
the world's
largest dharmic country it has the
largest number of buddhists
practicing buddhists in the world
despite it being officially
a marxist communist atheist country
china has more than 200 million
practicing buddhists even today so
buddhism once again it integrated itself
in chinese
society it uh synchronized itself with
the taoist beliefs and practices
so a person who practices buddhism in in
china today
would also integrate elements of taoism
in their day-to-day life and in their
traditions
so all polytheistic traditions are
extremely
accepting of other cultures especially
similar polytheistic cultures
and they integrate and syncretize very
readily
and you see this in japan as well as in
china
so great question
okay one more question this is from
shubham thank you shubham thank you very
much
the question is considering the
boundaries of the mongol empire
how they accommodated themselves so fast
to deserts rainforests
in contrast to clo to harsh cold
grasslands
environment has no effect on conquest
for mongols
well that's the thing about the mammals
they adapted very very quickly
they were accustomed to a very harsh
cold climate
they were accustomed to the deserts as
well there is this great gobi desert
between mongolia and china and parts of
mongolia are
very arid very dry even though they are
very cold so it's like a desert
so they were accustomed to a great deal
of hardship so going into a hotter
environment was not a big deal for them
it was just another form of hardship and
they had this
tight intense military discipline at all
times
so it was not difficult for them to
to adapt to different climates so for
example when they went to central asia
it was a different climate when they
went to iran it was a different climate
the south of china had a very different
climate especially yunnan and all that
and they tried invading uh japan
which they failed they tried invading so
the invasion was
of japan was under kublai khan
the first official emperor of the
chinese yuan dynasty
kublai khan was the grandson of genghis
khan
so so they were very adaptable they
they were accustomed to great deal of
hardships which is why they adapted so
fast
and like i said earlier they were always
ready to accept new technologies
so one of the criticisms i find on my
ching is khan video by certain people
is that the real reason they did not
invade india was because it was too hot
and because uh the more humid climate of
india was
deleterious to their to the to the
weapons that they had the essentially
especially the bow that they used
the thing is that the turks
who also came from a cold climate were
able to invade india without any
without any problem and they were able
to adapt to the hotter and more humid
environment of india
so why would the mongols not be able to
do that the mongols were
a far superior fighting force than the
turks
ever were so this argument absolutely
holds no
no merit at all the mongols
were able and they were capable of
invading and conquering
any kind of country any kind of terrain
any kind of climate
environment like you said actually
really
did not have any effect on the conquest
for mongols
chingas khan's grandsons were able to
conquer the hot
arid deserts of the islamic world they
went all the way to egypt
so they were an incredible fighting
force and
the environment didn't really did not
have any effect on
their on their conquests so thank you
for the question
okay this is from shiro tamashi thank
you sir
are the mongols descendants of huns and
how different are they from modern
turkic people
yes the mongols are the descendants of
the ancient
hunnic peoples and
the turks are also descendants of the
ancient
peoples so ethnically there is some
relationship between the turks
and the mongols before like i said
before the turks became muslims
they practiced the same cultures that
the mongols practice
today so there were elements of
tangerism and elements of buddhism
and the ons who invaded india
also integrated into indian society and
practiced hinduism and buddhism
as and when it spread in india
so in today's world the turks are very
different from the mongols first of all
if you look at the turkish people
they look like europeans they did not
look like the mongols
at all even though their own ancestors
were central asians right so what
happened was that
when the ancestors of today's turks
conquered
what is now turkey but what was then
known
as anatolia what they did was
they had this practice called bride
kidnapping
so it is a practice in which a young man
if he wants to marry
has to prove his bravery by sneaking
into the camp of a rival
tribe or confederation abducting a young
girl
and successfully bringing her back to
his own tribe so that was a test
of strength there was a test of whether
you are
uh you you you have reached your manhood
and whether you have the right to get
married or not so this is an ancient
turkic practice
it was also practiced throughout the
islamic world because
the turks became muslims and they
conquered most of the islamic world
so when they conquered anatolia which is
now turkey most of it
anatolia was essentially a greek land
it has been populated by greeks for
around 3000 years
so what they did was they practiced
their
custom of bright kidnapping on the local
women and slowly over the years
these turks started to look like
europeans and today they look
entirely like europeans they don't look
like the original turks at all
so today's turks are ethnically
europeans they're ethnically greeks and
armenians
right and they practice
the some elements of the old turkic
culture especially the turkish language
and they practice islam so their culture
is very different
from the culture of the mongolian people
today their ethnicity is totally
different they are now ethnically
european
and their language has some relationship
with the
modern mongolian language so that i hope
answers your question thank you
let me see if there are more questions
stanzing sir anything about ladakh
history salad
is a very interesting piece of
uh territory beautiful it is uh
quite desolate and barren it can get
really hot in the summer it gets really
really cold in the winter
the people of ladakh are ethnically
i would say tibetan right so that
is the reason why the chinese are trying
to claim ladakh that's why they have
captured aksai chin and there is the
there is the logical so supposedly
logical thought process
behind the the their claims towards
indian territory
so the people of ladakh are an extension
of the tibetan people
they are ethnically and culturally
tibetans
they practice buddhism and it
it's uh ladakh has uh always been
at least for the past thousand or
fifteen hundred years
of buddhist land it's had a great deal
of influence from tibetan buddhism which
is
mostly vajrayana and tantric buddhism
so that's briefly about ladakh history
it's a beautiful territory great people
very nice friendly beautiful people i
will go into
that in more detail in a future episode
but thank you for the question
okay some more questions about the
mongols
one second
okay another super chat question uh
thank you did ancient india have any
contact with the mayan civilization
or american continent red indians
excellent question we do not have
any evidence today
but there is a lot of circumstantial
evidence
which has thus far not been proven by
science
by hard science because nobody has
bothered to look into it
so the science of genetics may provide
clues
and archaeology may provide clues there
does seem to be some sort of
relationship
culturally and even to some extent
genetically between
india and the ancient indigenous peoples
of the two american continents we
know very well that indians in ancient
times undertook
very very large very
uh long naval voyages
for example we know for a fact
that the aboriginal indigenous people of
australia
have about 10 to 12 indian ancestry
and this indian ancestry entered
australia about four
and a half thousand years ago which
means that indians went by sea
crossed the indian ocean and went all
the way to northern australia
right this happened four and a half
thousand years ago
when the harappan era of indian
civilization was in full force
so indians had the capability to
undertake very long sea voyages
so it is not inconceivable that they may
have even gone further
and gone all the way to south america or
north america by sea
it is possible and you do see
interesting parallels between indian
culture
and the culture of the indigenous
americans
and there is this indian historian
called bikshu chamanlal
who wrote a book about this about a
century or so ago
and that book was where i i believe it
was banned by some
by by the united states
i think it was banned i'm not sure i'll
have to check it
but yes this has been remarked upon so
we do not have as of today
hard undisputable evidence of any
contact between india
ancient india and the ancient mayas or
the other peoples of america
but there is circumstantial evidence
historians
especially in the west are tr have been
trying to deny
indian history for a very long time so i
think in the future things may change
but as of today
we don't have hard evidence but it's a
very interesting topic thank you for the
question
okay this is by shiro tamashi thank you
sir
is it true that the white hounds waged
war and were defeated by skandaga
yes the white horns the heptalights the
shweta hunas
did try to invade india on several
occasions there were many waves
of invasions and they were defeated by
emperor skanda gupta skanda gupta
took a wow that he would not eat food in
a dish
and he would not sleep in a bed until he
defeated the huns
so he he decided that he would he would
eat food in a
leaf and he would sleep on the floor
until he had saved india from the huns
and he succeeded he kicked them out of
india
after emperor's kandakupta died
there were further waves of invasions
from the shweta hunas
and they did succeed to some extent in
conquering
certain territories in northern india
and they integrated assimilated in
india's population
harmoniously they adopted hinduism
buddhism and the local
practices and they eventually turned out
to be very good
kings and they became indians so they
did not impose a foreign culture
or foreign values or foreign religion on
india they became indians
so i appreciate what they did so yes the
white house did wage war in india
and eventually they became indians very
interesting part of history
and like i have said before they are
very much related to today's mongols so
that's an interesting connection
thank you for this question
okay this is a question by arjun p
thank you very much okada was the third
son
so why was he the chief good question
so what happened was that chingas khan
had
three or four sons uh
the first one was jochi whose paternity
was under question
the second one was i believe chagatai
the
and if i am not mistaken he may have had
more sons
with other wives he had he had multiple
wives
but these are the sons of the first wife
whose name was borthe so okada was the
third son but he was
selected by changes khan to be the next
khan of the mongols after chingishan's
death
so ching is khan decided this and
announced this in public
long before he died that ogde would
succeed him
as the great khan of the mongols so
there was no law in mongolia that that
that prescribed that the oldest son
should be should be the next
ruler it was all up to the current ruler
he could decide
whoever he wanted he could even decide
somebody not related to him
to be the next khan so essentially when
a khan
died in mongolia there was something
called a kurultai
which was an assembly of the law of the
lower chiefs
of the lower smaller khans and they
would essentially get together
and elect the next khan so it was a
quasi-democratic process
but usually the person who was nominated
by the previous khan to be the next khan
usually it was that person who was
elected by
by the kurultai so ching is khan decided
that ogedai was the most suitable
to be the great khan of the mongols not
his other two sons because
i believe he saw more ability in ogadai
than the other two or the other three
sons so it was all about
merit and capability not about seniority
or rank
so it was a very democratic kind of
society
it was a it was very much a meritocracy
and that is one of the secrets of the
success of the mongols it is
that's why this empire succeeded to the
extent that it did
because it promoted merit and not
nepotism i mean definitely it was the
son of the khan who became the
next khan but it was the best son not
the oldest son
so that's how it went good question
thank you
okay
i think uh
thank you so much appreciate it thank
you
okay this is a question by grip get it
thank you so much can you criticize
anything about ching is khan well that's
a good question
maybe he could have killed fewer people
we do not know exactly how many people
he killed
during his conquests the number that is
usually thrown around is 40 million
which is a fantastically large number
but even if we believe that it was 40
million people that he killed during his
conquests
and if we divide that number by the
by the area in square kilometers of the
territory he conquered
then the number of deaths per square
kilometer is
not greater than the number of deaths
that timur caused
or people like napoleon caused or people
like mao caused
in fact it is much less than the number
of deaths per kilometer
caused during the uh during the
bangladesh genocide of 1971 for example
so if you look at it from a realistic
perspective
the number of deaths he caused per
square kilometer of conquest
even if we take the ridiculous figure of
40 million
it is still not that excessive
when you conquer when somebody conquers
a territory there's gonna be fighting
there's gonna be warfare
so so a number of deaths is
unfortunately a byproduct of conquest
there's no two ways around it but what
would i criticize about shingiskan i
really
that's a fascinating question and i
haven't thought about it
so as of now i don't think i have any
criticisms of this guy
maybe he could have conquered more or
maybe he should have conquered india
and freed india from the tyranny of the
turks
yes i would say that is my criticism of
ching is khan
he should have conquered india and freed
us from this tyranny
that's the one thing he missed doing in
his life and that's why we have
this map instead of what it should have
been
all right thank you for the question let
me
find some more questions
dr heinz once again thank you sir what
about starting our civilization on other
planets
well which civilization is that is it
indian civilization is it chinese
civilization is it the western
capitalism
that is the question whichever country
succeeds in colonizing other planets
is going to export their culture and
civilization over there
so currently the world is under the sway
of western capitalism
which believes in never-ending expansion
it believes in never-ending quarter upon
quarter profits
and and continuous unending
infinite expansion on a finite planet
and it is this world view
that has led to the climate change
problem that we are facing today
it has led to the incredible pollution
we see in the oceans
and the mountains of garbage that is
exported from the west
into the third world nations because
they want to keep their countries clean
so this this world view and this
way of life is not sustainable
today they are trying to blame india and
china for pollution
this problem that the world is facing is
entirely created by the western world
starting from the so-called industrial
revolution when they started dumping
enormous amounts of of pollution into
the atmosphere
the global warming the atmospheric
pollution
the deforestation that we see today the
mountains of plastic
trash in our oceans it has all been done
by the west
this culture of disposability throw
everything use it once and throw away
so if this is the culture we're going to
export to other planets
then we as a as a species are doomed
because if we trash the earth and move
to mars we're gonna trash mars in no
time
and then where do we go so you know what
we need to first figure out what we want
to be like
which value system are we going to
embrace
as a whole we should do that before we
move on to other
planets so that's my answer thank you
for the question
this is by rajat mathur thank you rajat
the role of horses in conquest
it was the role of horses in
chingaskhan's
conquests was a central role none of it
would have happened without
the incredible mongolian pony
so the mongolian pony is a small animal
it is not as large as the arabian horse
it is a smaller horse but it is
extremely
hardy it has immense endurance
and it is perfect for the kind of
warfare the kind of blitzkrieg warfare
the mongols waged
so the mongols would never have been
able to conquer
the empire that they created without the
horse not even
100th of it so the role of horses in the
conquest was
a central role it is the key ingredient
to the success the mongols enjoyed good
question thank you
okay
this is an interesting question it's by
god of gore
why was shingis khan's tomb never found
why does it remain a mystery so this
is one of the biggest mysteries of all
time isn't it why has his tomb never
been found
where is tringas khan's tomb and and
people from the west have been seeking
his tomb
since the time of kublai khan his
grandson so marco polo
the italian merchant and traveler
went to china during marco polo's time
he spent a few years in marco polo's
court
and he heard of the story that changes
khan's tomb was
he heard a very fantastic story about
about his funeral
it said that everybody who saw the
funeral procession was killed
and an enormous hole was dug his body
was uh was buried there
and the ground was stamped over by
horses and the river was diverted over
the area so that nobody could ever find
it
and then all the soldiers and people who
participated in the funeral procession
they were also killed so no one knows
today even at
the time of marco polo where this tomb
was
and the belief in among western
historians and west
and in the west is that chinggis khan
khan's tomb
must have must have enormous amount of
treasure so whoever discovers this tomb
will become the richest person in the
world and that's why there has been this
mad
rush for centuries to discover the
location
of chingaskhan's tomb even now people
are trying to
go to mongolia and discover this tomb
there have been a couple of national
geographic documentaries as well
about the location of this tomb it has
never been found
and i'm gonna tell you something his
tomb is never going to be found
it remains a mystery because it is the
it is it was decided to keep it a
mystery
so chingaskhan was not a stupid person
he knew
what happens to the tombs of conquerors
those tombs are eventually discovered
and desecrated
take the mughal emperor akbar
the turkic emperor akbar after he died
a century or so after he died delhi was
conquered by the six
his tomb was ransacked and his bones
were fed to the dogs of delhi that's
what happened to akbar
if you look at the tomb of timur it was
opened by soviet archaeologists his body
his skeleton was taken out it was
disarticulated
it was subjected to all kinds of medical
and other tests
his skull was used as a model for
reconstructing his face
so it is essentially a desecration of
his tomb
and this has happened to emperors in
egypt and
all kinds of other people so chhingiskan
knew what happens
when the tomb of a conqueror is
discovered
especially when it contains treasure
there are two robbers everywhere
now the mongols had a practice called
sky burial
it was a practice that was also present
and prevalent in tibet
so when somebody dies their body is
exposed on a hilltop
to the elements it is devoured by
vultures and crows and other birds
and it goes back to the nature and its
spirit is carried away
to wherever it is supposed to go it's
called a sky burial
it is a legitimate funerary practice in
mongolia
and shingis khan died in china he died
during the
reconquest of the shisha dynasty in
northern china
now his ancestral homeland is the
kantikan mountains in northern mongolia
which is
approximately 1500 kilometers away now
to transport his body all the way back
to mongolia would take several months
and his body would decompose and rot
in the in the meanwhile and i don't
think the mongols
would want to subject that body that the
the body of their great khan
to to such humiliation so what i believe
is that after chingashan died his body
was subjected to a sky funeral a sky
burial
and that is what happened i don't think
his tomb
is present anywhere in mongolia i don't
think he was entombed anywhere
i think his body was given up as a sky
sky funeral
which is a very dignified thing and
because it happened so far away because
his death happened so far away from his
from the place where he was born i think
that is the most logical explanation
of how his funeral took place
and like i have explained before he was
not interested in wealth
he was never motivated by a desire to
get wealthy and therefore this
belief that his tomb would contain
unimaginable amounts of wealth
it is a ridiculous assumption so my
belief
my my strong conviction is that he was
his funeral was a sky funeral and his
tomb doesn't even exist
and that's why his tomb has never been
found and that's why it will remain a
mystery to those who believe that he was
buried somewhere right that's a good
question
one more question by lena mehta ching is
khan versus alexander who conquered more
zhang is khan
absolutely he conquered more territory
than anybody else
in human in in recorded history
he conquered more territory in 30 years
than
all of the roman empires combined were
able to conquer in more than three
centuries
just imagine that and alexander's
conquest don't even come close
to what shingis khan achieved so there
is
no comparison genghis khan was far
greater as a conqueror
than alexander all right
uh
okay i'm gonna take one more question
for today and that will be the last
question
let me see
okay any scientific or philosophy
advancement by
khan by chinese khan no the mongolians
were not scientists
the mongolians were not philosophers
they believed in absorbing science
technology philosophy culture from
others
and there is nothing wrong about that
so their own culture was
tenorism like i have explained it was a
polytheistic belief system
and they syncretized it with tibetan
buddhism so what happened was that
during
the rule of chinese khan's grandson
kublai khan
what happened was that kublai khan made
tibetan buddhism
the de facto state religion of the
mongol empire across
china and across everywhere everywhere
else
so essentially the the relationship
between tibet and mongolia was that of a
teacher and a student tibet was the guru
mongolia was the shishya it was a
guru-shishi relationship
it was not the relationship between a
master and
a subject mongolia did not ever conquer
tibet tibet was a protectorate of
mongolia
mongolia offered protection and in
exchange tibet offered it its spiritual
guidance as a teacher so mongolia
absorbed tibetan
buddhism which is a mix of vajrayana and
tantra
to the most part so mongolia is
strongly strongly influenced by indian
culture
via tibet so that's what happened
so no scientific or philosophy
advancement by the mongols they were
influenced by
mainly india culturally and they absorb
technology and science from
everywhere they could and that's why
they succeeded
okay i'm going to take one more question
one last question
this is by jay dixit
what is your opinion about the dark past
many people say that chingas khan had a
very dark past which made him rude
he had killed a large number of people
for power
any evidence so when you conquer the
greatest
empire you have in the history of
humanity the greatest empire
known to us it's going to cause number
of deaths
now when the pakistanis tried to retain
bangladesh
they killed about two or three million
bangladeshis in about seven months
now the number that is attributed to
ching is khan is 40 million by some
historians
there is no real evidence for it but
this is what they claim
right so even if you see if you even if
you
assume that this 40 million figure is is
correct
you have to take into account the
enormous territory he conquered
when you conquered a kingdom when you
conquered a piece of land
you have to fight for it there is
warfare and in warfare
people die whether you like it or not
so he conquered an enormous amount of
territory
there is going to be a number of deaths
associated with it
and he always conquered or invaded other
kingdoms in retaliation
he did not ever start a war but whenever
war was forced upon it upon him
he retaliated and he finished it by
defeating the by defeating the offending
party
so he did not enjoy killing there is no
evidence that he was a cruel person
in any way whatsoever he was a very just
ruler
he was a very principled ruler but he
did conquer enormous lands
and therefore there were a number of
deaths we do not really know
how many people died during his
conquests but
i am sure lots of people did die as a
as a byproduct of his conquests so
that's
about it for shingis khan
okay one bonus question by akshay chobe
what is
my way to study history do i make notes
of all that i study
my way of studying history has been to
read as much as i can
so i read books i read lots of books i i
have read
more books than i have bought and i have
more and i have bought more books than i
can possibly read
so i have been doing this since i was
about seven or eight years old i was
always very curious
and it is because of curiosity that i am
able to retain the kind of knowledge
that i have
now i don't read books in their entirety
if i find a book
about a specific topic i read the
relevant portion
if it is interesting i may read the
whole book but typically i read some
portions of books not the entire book
and i read some books several times i
read some books only once
and apart from books i have read
thousands possibly of
of research papers and articles i even
read
magazine articles i even read blog posts
i even read books that i know are
incorrect like books about the arena
invasion theory
because i want to know the perspective
of the other side
so i have been reading for a very very
long time i enjoy reading i am a very
curious person
and that is how i study history uh in
today's age
you may not need to read so much you can
you can absorb
information via podcasts via programs
such as what i am doing today
by documentaries etc so there are many
other ways of
absorbing knowledge today but the main
thing is you have to remain
curious and you have to have an open
mind you should be
open to new ideas and new perspectives
if you do that then you will
be able to enjoy learning history and
the reason we hate
learning history in school is because we
are forced to memorize
dates that is a stupid thing you don't
need to memorize dates to understand
history
you just need to know roughly when
something happened so when did the turks
conquer uh istanbul
constantinople it was somewhere in the
15th century
maybe in the 1450s or thereabouts i
don't remember the exact date
i don't have to all i have to understand
is the cause and effect chain of history
and i need to know roughly when
something happened so memorizing dates
is
is not the way to to learn history if
you do that all the joy is sucked out of
of learning history so that's how i do
it
maybe that's something that you could uh
take some ideas from okay this is the
absolute last question
it's by divya jain thank you divya is it
is there any chance all people might
have been part of only one lineage of
human beings
occupying any particular part of the
world and then they migrated and the
history eventually disintegrated along
with time
so this is the this is the main core
premise of the out of africa theory
that humanity originates in africa at
least
our ancestral lineages all
uh originate in africa
so today's human beings are homo sapiens
it is one species
out of many there have been many species
and subspecies of humans in the past
we are the only surviving species homo
sapiens
we have had homo neanderthales we had
have the denisovan humanists
we have had the homo florences and many
others
so all of these went extinct at
different times
homo sapiens us is the only surviving
lineage of humans
and from all the evidence that we have
as of today
we originate in africa and it was one
group of humans who came
out of africa migrated to india and from
india
went in all directions in the world so
yes your conjecture is in fact
the currently accepted uh
version of history that science uh is
able to give us
so good question all right this
this has to be the last question where
do i see india in 50 years of time
technologically and culturally
thank you sir i don't know
i hope to see india regain its
civilizational status
and to do that we have to embrace
science
science and technology we have to
embrace science as a nation again
we have always been a very scientific
people
we have been at the forefront of science
and technology and astronomy
and mathematics the the entire science
see all of the science that we have
today is founded
on a bed on a bedrock of indian science
which was exported out of india about a
thousand years ago
it spread to the arabic world the
islamic world and from there into europe
and all that was used as the foundation
of what
we have taken forward as modern science
today
so india needs to go back to its roots
it needs to
embrace science and technology and india
needs to rediscover its own indigenous
culture which i believe is superior
to the western capitalistic
uh materialistic and extremely
destructive culture that we have today
so i hope to see india at the forefront
of the world in 50 years time
i hope to see india take the lead in
exploring space
because the two or three countries which
will be at the forefront of space
exploration
in the 21st century are going to be the
two or three nations that lead the world
so that's where i hope to see india in
50 years time i hope that comes true
thank you very much everybody for
participating this was great
fun and i'm going to end this now
and i will see you again very soon i'll
see you again tomorrow
thank you everybody for all your
questions for for the for all the
comments
apologies to those uh questions i could
not take
keep asking me questions over time i
will take everyone's questions
thank you very much take care have a
good night and i will see you tomorrow
bye